Hello everyone. Have a good conference so far? Are you having a good conference so far?
Good, wonderful. I have a message for you that I hope will be a comforting message for
folks who believe that their skill set is no longer worth anything in this new age, which is I believe
that software fundamentals matter now more than they actually ever have. And I'm a teacher,
and I have been recently teaching a course called Claude Code for Real Engineers, nice and provocative,
and in the process of kind of working on this course, I had to come up with a curriculum about
AI coding, which is a bit of a nightmare because things are changing all the time, right? AI is a
whole new paradigm. We need to chuck out all of the old rules, surely, so that we can bring in the
new stuff. And there's a kind of movement that has come up around this, which is the specs to code
movements. And the specs to code movement says that, okay, you can write a specification about how
an application is supposed to work. Then you can use AI to turn it into code. If there's a problem
with the application, you then go back to the spec. You don't really look at the code, you just change
the spec, you run the compiler again, and you end up with more code. Raise your hand if you've heard of
that. Keep your hand raised if you've tried it. Okay, I've tried it too. You can put your hands down.
What I noticed was I would run it, and I would try not to look at the code,
but I would look at the code. And I realized I would get code out, first of all, and now run it,
I would get worse code. And I did it again, I got even worse code. And I got it again, I kept running
the compiler, kept running the compiler, and I would just end up with garbage. Raise your hand if
that's happened to you. Yes, I don't think this works. The idea that we can just ignore the code and
just have the code, let it manage itself, is just sort of by coding by another name.
And I didn't believe that back then. I thought, okay, how do I fix the compiler? How do I make it so
that it doesn't produce bad code each time, or worse code? And so I thought, okay, I need to explain
to the LLM in English what a good code base looks like. Let me dig out one of my old favorite books,
which is a philosophy of software designed by John Alsterhouds. Go on Amazon, get it.
And he has a definition for what bad code looks like. He calls it complex code. Complexity is
anything related to the structure of a software system that makes it hard to understand and modify
the system, right? So a bad code base is a code base that's hard to change. If you can't change a
code base without causing bugs, then it's a bad code base. Good code bases are easy to change.
So I thought, oh, that was good. Let's try another book. Let's try the parametric programmer.
Go on Amazon, get it. They have a whole chapter on something called software entropy.
And this is exactly what I was seeing. Entropy is the idea that things tend towards disaster
and floating away from each other and collapse. And this is exactly how most software systems
behave, too, is that every time you make a change to a code base, if you're only thinking about that
change, not thinking about the design of the whole system, your code base is going to get worse and
worse and worse. And that's what I was seeing. Everything inside the specs to code idea that you
just run the compiler again and again was making worse code. Now, there's an idea that sort of drives
the specs to code movements, which is that code is cheap. Raise your hand if you've heard that phrase
before, that code is cheap. Yeah. Well, I don't think this is right. I think code is not cheap. In
fact, bad code is the most expensive it's ever been. Because if you have a code base that's hard
to change, you're not able to take all of the bounty that AI can offer because AI in a good code base
actually does really, really well. And this means good code bases matter more than ever,
which means software fundamentals matter more than ever. That's the thesis of this talk.
So let's actually get into practical stuff. I'm going to talk about different failure modes that
you may have experienced or you may not have experienced the AI and how you can avoid them by just
going back to all books and looking at software practices. So I'm good. So the first one is that the AI
didn't do what I wanted. You know, I thought I had a good idea in my head and the AI just did something
totally different or it did some like specs that I, you know, it just made something I didn't want.
Raise your hand if you've hit this mode. Cool. Okay. Well, this is what they say in the pragmatic
programmer is that no one knows exactly what they want. Is that you and the AI, there is a
communication barrier there, right? And so when you're talking to the AI, that's kind of like the AI
doing its requirements gathering. It's basically working out from you what it is that you need. And
I realize that there was another book, Frederick P. Brooks, the design of design. And it talks about
this idea called the design concept. Is that when you have more than one person designing something
together, you have this idea sort of floating between you, this ephemeral idea of the thing that
you're building. And that thing that you're building or the idea of it is called the design concept.
It's not an asset. It's not something you can put in a markdown file. It is the invisible sort of
theory of what you're building. And so I thought, okay, that's what's going on. Me and the AI don't share
a design concept. So I came up with a skill. The skill is very, very simple. It's called Grill Me.
And it looks like this. Interview me relentlessly about every aspect of this plan until we reach a
shared understanding. Walk down each branch of the design tree, which is another thing from Frederick
P. Brooks, resolving dependencies between decisions one by one. This skill is like, the repo containing
this skill has like 13,000 stars or something like. It just went nuts, went viral, people love this
thing. These couple of lines, it means the AI asks you like 40 questions, 60 questions. I've had
it ask people a hundred questions before it's satisfied. They've reached a shared understanding.
And it means it turns the AI into a kind of adversary where it's just continually pinging new ideas
and trying to reach a shared understanding. And that means that the conversation that you then
generates, you can take that and turn it into product requirements documents or something.
Or if it's a small change, you can just do, turn it directly into issues. And then your AFK agent
will then pick it up. And don't add me on this, but I personally believe this is better than the
default plan mode in the tool that I use, which is called code. Plan mode is extremely eager to
create an asset. It really wants to just create a plan and start working. Whereas I think it's
a lot nicer to reach a shared design concept first. So that's tip number one. Now, failure mode number
two is that the AI is just way too verbose. It's like you're almost talking across purposes with the AI.
Raise your hand if you feel this, if you ever experience that failure mode. Yeah, it's kind of like
the AI is like talking just using too many words to try to communicate what it's doing. It's not
like you're talking using the same language. And this to me felt very, very familiar, right? If you've
ever been a developer for a long time and you've worked with, let's say, domain experts, someone building
an application, let's say the domain expert wants you to build something on microchips, you have no
idea what microchips are. You need to establish some kind of shared language, right? Because otherwise
they're going to be using terms you don't understand. You're going to be translating that into code
that maybe you don't even understand. And certainly the domain expert won't. And so there's this kind of
language gap between you and the domain experts. And so I went back to domain driven design,
DDD. This is something I'm still kind of on the edge of exploring, but everything I'm reading about
DDD is just music to my ears. I freaking love it. And DDD has a concept of a ubiquitous language.
With ubiquitous language, conversations among developers and expressions of the code and
conversations with domain experts are all derived from the same domain model. It's essentially a
markdown file full of a list of terms that you and the AI have in common. And you really focus on
those terms and you really make sure that they're aligned with what it actually means. And you use
them all the time in the code when you're talking about the code when you're talking to domain experts
or in our case when you're talking with AI. So I made a skill. This skill is the ubiquitous language
skill. Basically just scans your code base, looks for terminology and then creates a markdown file,
creates the ubiquitous language markdown file, a bunch of markdown tables with all of the terminology.
And this then I pass it to the AI and I'm able to read it to and I actually have it open all the time
when I'm grilling with the AI and planning and that. And what I noticed by reading the thinking
traces of the AI not only improves the planning but it allows the AI to think in a less of a both way
and actually means that the implementation is more aligned with what you actually planned.
So this has absolutely been a powerhouse. It's an unbelievably good. So that's tip number two.
Create a shared language with the AI. So okay, let's imagine that you've aligned with the AI. You
know what it is you're supposed to be building. The AI has built the right thing but it doesn't work.
Raise your hands if that's happened to you. Yep, just doesn't work. Well, there's an obvious thing that
we can do to make that better which is we can use feedback loops. We can use static types,
you know, if you're not using text scripts, that's crazy. If you're building a front end app and you're
not giving the lm access to the browser so it can look around, absolutely needs that. And you
obviously also need automated tests. And one sort of thing I noticed here is that even with these
feedback loops, the lm doesn't use them very well. It doesn't kind of like get the most out of its
feedback loops in the way that a veteran developer would. And so it does, what it tends to do is just
does way too much at once. It will produce a huge amounts of code and then think, oh, I should
probably type track that actually. Or I should, you know, maybe check a test on that or maybe do
something like that. And this in the pragmatic programmer that describes as outrunning your
headlights, as essentially driving too fast because the rate of feedback is your speed limit.
The rate of feedback is your speed limit which means that you should be testing as you go taking
small deliberate steps. And the AI by default is really not very good at that. And so skill number
three is TDD. You should be using test driven developments because TDD forces the lm to really take
small steps. You create a test first, you make that test pass and then you refactor the code to make
it nicer and consider the design. The issue here is that testing is really hard. Testing is always
been hard. And the reason for that is there are a ton of different decisions you need to make when
you write a test. You need to figure out how big a unit do you want to test. You need to figure out
what to mock. You need to figure out what behaviors do you even want to test in the first place.
And all of these decisions are dependent. So if you are testing a really big units like an entire
massive application, then it might be quite flaky. You might not want to test that many behaviors.
If you only test this unit, you need to mock this unit. It's all interlinked. And I've been thinking
about this for years from my entire development career. And what we notice is that good code bases are
easy code bases to test. So here we're starting to get back to the idea of code being important.
Is that the better your code bases, the better your feedback loops are because you're able to
give better feedback to the LEM. It produces better code. And so I thought what does a good code
base, what does a testable code base look like? Again, we go to John Alsterhaut. He talks about having
deep modules in your code base. Not shallow modules, not lots of modules that expose
kind of lots of functions. They should be relatively few large deep modules with simple interfaces.
Let's compare them quickly. Deep modules, lots of functionality hidden behind a simple interface,
hiding the complexity. You can look inside the deep module if you want to, but you don't need to,
you can just use the interface. Shallow modules, not much functionality, complex interface.
And I'll just wait if you did take the photos. Shallow modules in a code base kind of look like this.
We have a ton of different tiny little blobs that the AI has to walk through and navigate.
And this is really hard for the AI to explore actually. And so often what you'll see is if you have
a code base like this, which AI is really good at creating code bases like this, is that you'll have
a situation where AI doesn't understand what your code is doing. It will attempt to explore the code,
but because it's poorly laid out, filled with shallow modules, it doesn't maybe get to the right
module in time or doesn't understand all the dependencies, all that stuff. It doesn't understand your
code. And so what does a code base full of deep modules look like? Well, it looks like this,
where it's the same code, but it's just structured inside boundaries where you have these interfaces
on the top. And these interfaces, you should probably have a lot of control over them and design
them really well. Otherwise, you know, AI might mess up the design. But the implementation, you can
kind of leave that to the AI a bit. So how do you turn a code base that looks like this into a
code base that looks like that? Well, I've got a skill for that. Improve code base architecture.
Turns out this is not, it's quite complicated to do this, but it's just like a set of steps that
you could reusably do again and again. You just sort of explore the code base, look for opportunities
where there's code that's kind of related and the wrapper of that in a deep module.
And this is a testable code base because the boundaries around this code are so, so simple. You test
at the interface, you verify using that interface, and you're good to go. And so this is a code base
that rewards TDD. But how about failure mode number six? Which is your, okay, let's say your feedback
loops are working. Let's say that things are kicking into gear. You're able to ship more code than you
ever have before. But your brain can't keep up. Right? Raise your hand if you felt more tired
than you have ever before in your development career. Yeah, me too. It's knackering. And I think that
this is a code base that actually makes it harder for your brain because you as well as the AI need to
keep all of that information in your head. Whereas this, not only is it simpler for you to read and
understand, it also means you can kind of treat these modules or these deep modules as gray boxes.
You can kind of say, okay, I'm going to just design the interface, but I'm not going to worry too much,
or not review the implementation too much. You can do this obviously with things that are less critical
in your application. I can't do this with various things like finance or whatever. But in many,
many modules in your app, you don't need to think about the implementation too much as long as you
have a testable boundary outside the module. And as long as you understand its purpose and can design it
from the outside, I have found this has really saved my brain because I can just go, okay, the AI
I'll let you handle what's inside the big blob. I'm just going to test from the outside and verify it.
So that's tip number five. Design the interface, delegate the implementation.
But this means that whenever we're touching the code, whenever we're planning stuff,
we need to think about and be aware of the modules in our application. We need to know that map
really well. It needs to be part of our ubiquitous language. We need to build it into our planning
skills as well. So my right to PRD, inside the PRD, I'm specific about the module changes and the
interfaces inside those modules. How they're being modified, I'm thinking about them all the time.
And this comes from Kent Beck, invest in the design of the system every day.
And this is the core of it, right? Because specs the code, we are not investing in the design of
the system. We are divesting from it. We're getting rid of that. Whereas this, I think, is absolutely
key. And so code is not cheap. That's the message I want you to take away. Code is important.
And if we think about AI as a really great on the ground programmer, a kind of tactical programmer,
a sergeant on the ground making the code changes, you need someone above that. You need someone
thinking on the strategic level. And that's you. And that requires software fundamental skills that
we've been using for 20 years, from longer. Now if you were interested in any of the skills I put up
here, it's in the GitHub repo, MacBook skills. And if you're interested in the training that I do,
any free stuff, I'm on YouTube, I'm on Twitter, but I'm also an AI hero.dev,
where I have a newsletter that you can check out. Thank you so much. I hope that this gives you
confidence in this new AI age. So you can actually make a good impact. Thank you.